HUGO BLANCO SANDOVAL

Senior Software Engineer



- **J** (206) 856-2807
- Gilbert, AZ
- in linkedin.com/in/hugoblancosandoval

Web technologies have always been my passion and, thankfully, that's the path my career has taken me: from small startups all the way to Amazon. In my 16 years in the industry I have seen a lot, from web services and jQuery to streaming RESTful APIs with complex React SPAs and always but with an eye on quality and efficiency.

EDUCATION

B.S. in Engineer in Computer Systems

Instituto Tecnológico Superior de Uruapan



Uruapan, Michoacan, Mexico,

Languages

English, Spanish

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer

Cogniac Inc. May 2023 - Nov 2023 | Gilbert, AZ

A part of the UI team, I took care of building and maintaining Cogniac web app which allows you to build workflows and pipelines based on the Cogniac's computer vision Al-driven abilities.

I was also part of the Ember to React migration initiative, which allowed me to:

- Design and implement, in the selected stack, the generic components that would be used during the migration. We used a React with Typescript and a couple of off-the-shelf component libraries, HeadlessUI and TanStack.
- Implemented components that replicated functionality form the original application.
- Collaborated with the team members to design the user experience of the new application.
- Presented the functionality developed during our sprints in our weekly demos.
- We used Vite, React, Vitest, Cypress, TanStack, Headless, TypeScript and SASS with Tailwind along with Figma and Untitled UI to design the components

Senior Software Engineer

Bttn Inc. Feb 2023 - May 2023 | Seattle, WA

I lead the effort to migrate the Bttn store backend and frontend from Shopify to BigCommerce, which allow the company to increase their capacity to handle traffic and availability of the site.

- Mentored other team members. The team had a couple of recently graduated engineers, so I was able to help them grow, acquire and execute best engineering and coding practices.
- Participated in the design, architecture and implementation of the code base that feeds BigCommerce and several other services, using Python, Celery, DJango, Flask, Zappa and AWS.
 - I was the technical lead in the development of one of the services that interacts with the storefront hosted on BigCommerce. We were building this service with Python, Flask, Zappa and AWS.

Senior Frontend Engineer

Aspiration Partners, Inc July 2022 - December 2022 | Seattle, WA I was part of the UI team that developed and maintained the web app that allowed the company to give support to customers.

Aspiration's customer service app was a React-based application with a

Technologies

JavaScript, Node, TypeScript, React, React Hooks, HTML, CSS, SASS, Backbone, jQuery, SQL, NoSQL, AWS, Web Services, RESTFul services, HTMX, Web Components, PWAs, Unit Testing (Mocha, Jest, Cypress, Vitest, Cucumber), Git, Agile, C#, Python, Clojure, ClojureScript, Linux (Slackware, Ubuntu, Debian)

GraphQL service that served as the main source of data.

I also worked as the team liaison, coordinating with external teams to gather requirements, create and establish priorities and set up the pipeline of projects and requests for the team.

Senior Frontend Engineer

Skytap Inc. December 2015 - July 2022 | Seattle, WA

During my time with the company, I was part of multiple initiatives that helped advance Skytap's relationship with IBM plus, I was also a spearhead on the initiatives that opened up the association with Microsoft's Azure division to provide support to bare metal virtualization on their platform.

Skytap's original web app made heavy use of Backbone.js and jQuery and I was there for the (continuous) migration from Backbone views to React. I worked on keeping and integrating all the code we wrote in Backbone models which included all of our business logic.

- My duties included developing, creating, and modifying Skytap's Web application, which gives the user the ability to create, run and modify hosted virtual environments.
- Skytap's web client is a very complex application built using two
 main stacks: an in-house JavaScript framework, based on
 Backbone.js and a more recently one based on React and
 Redux; this application gives the user great control over their
 virtual environments and other productivity tools created
 around those virtual environments.
- I was one of the senior members of our team which allowed me to coach and mentor younger devs, something that I enjoy.

Software Developer I

Amazon Inc. / Software Developer

Oct 2013 - April 2015, Seattle, WA

Worked as part of Transaction Risk Management (TRMS) organization, working building platforms to ensure that every eCommerce transaction is trusted, safe and protected from fraud.

I worked with the Chargebacks team, in which we created software to handle a time of financial transaction known as a "chargeback": demand by a credit-card provider for a retailer to make good the loss on a fraudulent or disputed transaction. We created and maintained services that would take care of process and direct chargebacks to the correct financial entities.

Experience

Nearsoft Inc. (now Encora) / Software Developer

May 2007 - Sept 2013, Hermosillo, Sonora, Mexico

Nearsoft Inc. (now Encora) was a very developer centric company based in the Northwest region of Mexico, it worked only with companies based in the USA by building extension teams, not just doing outsourcing projects. The following is a list of the outstanding clients that I worked with while I was working with Nearsoft.

Ingrooves Fontana Inc. / Software Developer.

Worked on laying the foundations for a new internal rapid development framework, selecting technologies and patterns to be used in the service layer (although I have been part of the decision of technologies in all the other layers) where I have selected Python as a foundational language, RabbitMQ for our communications and developed a custom framework to interact with RabbitMQ, written in Python.

NextMed Inc. / Software Developer

Worked as Software Engineer extending an existing internal application (built using the.NET stack), coding new features and fixing bugs. I also created a web app using ASP.NET MVC 4.

Vertigo Software Inc. / Software Developer

Worked as a Software Engineer on different projects, most of them using the .NET stack and one participating in the development of an iOS application.

YottaMark Inc. / Software Developer

Worked as a Software Engineer on different projects, all of them using the .NET stack (.NET 2.0 to 3.5, SQL Server 2005 and 2008, ASP.NET, WinForms, WCF and ASMX web services).

During my time with this client, I developed a quality assurance tool, extended and debugged existing applications for their operations team (applications that print labels and interacted with their label generation systems) and designed and implemented applications that exploited the information in their systems.